<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Another word to the wise, shewing that the delay of justice, is great injustice. By displaying heavier grievances in petitions from severall counties to the House of Commons and letters to Parlament men, from Mr. John Musgrave Gentleman, one of the commissioners from Cumberland and Westmerland, for presenting their grievances to the Parliament. Who instead either of redressing those two counties grievances, or prosecuting the charge given in by him against Mr. Richard Barwis, a Parliament man, ... did illegally commit the said Mr John Musgrave to the Fleet, where he hath lain these 4. moneths, without any justice, on tryall of his businesse. ...</title>
            <author>Musgrave, John, fl. 1654.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89423</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M3144</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E323_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17785</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860269</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860269</idno>
            <idno type="VID">159548</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89423)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 159548)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 53:E323[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Another word to the wise, shewing that the delay of justice, is great injustice. By displaying heavier grievances in petitions from severall counties to the House of Commons and letters to Parlament men, from Mr. John Musgrave Gentleman, one of the commissioners from Cumberland and Westmerland, for presenting their grievances to the Parliament. Who instead either of redressing those two counties grievances, or prosecuting the charge given in by him against Mr. Richard Barwis, a Parliament man, ... did illegally commit the said Mr John Musgrave to the Fleet, where he hath lain these 4. moneths, without any justice, on tryall of his businesse. ...</title>
                  <author>Musgrave, John, fl. 1654.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, 1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "London feb: 20th 1645"; the second 6 in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Barwis, Richard.</term>
               <term>Justice, Administration of --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Denial of justice --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:159548:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ANOTHER WORD TO THE WISE, Shewing that the <hi>Delay of juſtice,</hi> is great inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. By diſplaying heavier grievances in petitions from ſeverall Counties to the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and letters to Parlament Men, from Mr. <hi>John Muſgrave</hi> Gentleman, one of the Commiſſioners from <hi>Cumberland</hi> and <hi>Weſtmerland,</hi> for preſenting their grievances to the Parliament.</p>
            <p>Who inſtead either of redreſſing thoſe two Counties grievances, or proſecuting the charge gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in by him againſt Mr. <hi>Richard Barwis,</hi> a Parliament man, for betraying his truſt, in placing Traytors and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant officers in chief places of command, to the apparant ruin thereof and landing of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels there, did illegally commit the ſaid Mr <hi>John Muſgrave</hi> to the Fleet, where he hath lain theſe 4. moneths, without any juſtice, or tryall of his buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>For refuſing to anſwer Interrogatories, otherwiſe then according to law by writing, or to ſtoop unto the arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary and illegall proceedings of a Committee, who admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the parties accuſed, to ſit with their hatts on, and committeth the accuſers to priſon, though they themſelves doe offer to ſuffer, if they prove not their charge by ſufficient witneſſes.</p>
            <q>Though band joyne in band, the wicked ſhall not be unpuniſhed. The righteous is more excellent then his neighbour, but the way of the wicked will deceive them. He that juſtifieth the wicked, and he that condemneth the juſt, even both thoſe are abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Lord. <bibl>
                  <hi>Pro. 11. 21.</hi> and <hi>12. 26.</hi> and <hi>17. 15.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare, 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:159548:2"/>
            <head>To our worthy and much reſpected friend, Mr. <hi>Iohn Muſgrave.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS time (that precious jewel) bringeth forth the truth of all things, ſo have we gained more knowledge of your juſt cauſe, and uniuſt ſufferings, ſince we publiſhed your laſt letters and Petitions, under the title of <hi>A word to the Wiſe,</hi> for we have not only received more letters and Petitions, which we have here alſo divulged, but likewiſe the coppie of an order from the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, againſt that little booke, of which order the words are theſe.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="notice">
                        <head>Die Martis 17. Ianuary, 1645.</head>
                        <p>The houſe tooke notice of a Pamphlet, intituled <hi>A word to the Wiſe, diſplaying great augmented grievances, and heavie preſſures of dangerous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence:</hi> And it is ordered, that it be referred to the Committee of Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, who are required to make a ſtrict inquitie after the Author, Printer, and divulger of the ſaid Pamphlet, and to give a ſpeedy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt thereof to the Houſe.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Here is a word to the Wiſe indeed! a great noiſe of hue and cry for a man that like worthy <hi>Nehemiah</hi> never ran away. It is a wonder that thoſe few men ſhould thinke all other men blind but themſelves. What Butcher is ſo idle and undiſcreet, as to ſend his blood-hounds abroad, to drive home an Ox, which he knoweth is already in his own back ſhop. Only it may be, that ſome time he will make great ſearch for his knife, whileſt is ſticks in his teeth. And is it not as great a wonder, that they doe offer thus to ſearch abroad for the Printer and divulger of that booke, and not ſeeke their owne ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>et priſon at home for the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor Mr. <hi>Iohn Muſgrave,</hi> and owner of the chiefe parts thereof, whoſe name is ſo eminent and often therein expreſſed? It is moſt certaine, that ſuch dealing cannot long proſper, more then <hi>Zimri</hi> did, who killed his maſter. But be of good comfort, the ſame God who ſent the Ravens to ſeed <hi>Eliah, Ebedmelech</hi> the black-more to comfort <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> &amp; King <hi>Pharoahs</hi> baker to deliver <hi>Ioſeph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> will have the like care of you, and all that ſtand in the gap either for religion or the juſt freedome of the nation: Great cauſe have we to be jealous of many whem we have truſted with all that is neareſt and dearest unto us in this world, and in whoſe defence ſo many thouſands of lives, and ſuch abundance of treaſures have been ſpent, and ſuch multitudes of Widowes and Orphans left in diſtreſſe; and ſtill though perſecuters and oppreſſors be changed, yet both perſecution and oppreſſion remaines. For although the Counſell table, Star-Chamber and High Commiſſion be put down, yee all the free born of this kingdome doe feele the power thereof tranſformed in another habite, and ſtill remaining in the Committees, as is too apparent by their manifold illegall proceedings to enſlave us. But our comfort is, that though the world ſhould turn upſide downe, and the mountaines fall into the ſea, yet it ſhall be well with thoſe that feare God. Fare well.</p>
            <div type="commitment">
               <pb facs="tcp:159548:2"/>
               <head>The Copy of the Commitment, <hi>25. Octob. 1645.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Upon Mr. <hi>Liſles</hi> report from the Committee, to which the Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions given in by Mr. <hi>John Muſgrave,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Oſmotherly,</hi> againſt Mr. <hi>Barvis</hi> a Member of this Houſe, was referred, Mr. <hi>Muſgrave</hi> refuſed to anſwer ſuch Interrogatories as were propounded unto him by the Committee, upon the Direction and Order of this Houſe.</p>
               <p>Reſolved, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>That Mr. <hi>John Muſgrave</hi> be forthwith committed priſoner to the Fleet, for his contemptuous refuſing to anſwer to ſuch Interrogatories as were propounded unto him by the Committee upon the directions of this Houſe, and that a Warrant do iſſue under M. Speakers hand, for the Commitment of him priſoner to the Fleet accordingly.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Hen. Elſyng. Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="warrant">
               <p>By vertue of an Order of the Houſe of Commons, dated <hi>25. Octob. 1645.</hi> Theſe are to will and require you forthwith upon the receipt hereof, you appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the body of Mr. <hi>John Muſgrave,</hi> and him ſafely deliver unto the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the Fleet, there to be kept priſoner, for his contempt to the ſaid Houſe, untill the ſaid Houſe take further order therein. And the ſaid Warden of the Fleet is hereby required to receive into his cuſtody; the ſaid <hi>John Muſgrave</hi> to be kept priſoner accordinlgy: for which, this ſhall be your warrant, dated <hi>27. Octob. 1645.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>William Lenthall,</hi> Speaker.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="note">
               <head>To the Serjant at Armes, attending the Houſe of Commons, or his Deputy. And to the Warden of the Fleet, or his deputy.</head>
               <p>I do appoint <hi>George Bragg,</hi> Gentleman, to be my lawfull Deputy to execute this Warrant, <hi>dated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7, Octob.</hi> 1645.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Edward Berkhead,</hi> Serjant at Armes,</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:159548:3"/>
            <head>The 27. day of the firſt moneth, 1646. there was a petition out of <hi>York-ſhire,</hi> preſented to the Parliament whereof the true copy here followeth. <hi>To the Right Honourable, the Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes, aſſembled in the Commons Houſe in Parliament. The humble Petition of many thouſands of the Wel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>affected in</hi> Yorkſhire.</head>
            <opener>Sheweth.</opener>
            <p>THat they ever looked on the Parliament, as the only refuge under God in this Kingdome, for the relief of the diſtreſſed Subject, from Popery, tyrannie and injuſtice, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have in and for the defence of Religion, the priviledges of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, the rights and libertie of the Subject; ventured their lives, ſpent their eſtates, and have been plundered of their goods, even to the utter undoing of many of their wives, children, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That of late many of the Kings partie ſome who have been in Arms, in open rebellion againſt the Parliament, others who have ſtood as neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, waiting to ſide with the ſtronger partie, and no way aſſiſting the Parliament (but by conſtraint, have by ſubtle ſpeeches, and clandeſtine wayes, gradually wound themſelves in to be Committees for the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and ſome to be Commanders; Who ſo palliate and vail their actions, with pretences of State, that the well-affected and friends of the Parliament, cannot have juſtice; or are ſo delayed in their juſt ſuits, that they are quite wearied out and diſcouraged.</p>
            <p>The Petitioners therfore humbly pray, this honourable Houſe to take the premiſes into ſerious and due conſideration, and for preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the great miſchiefe, that may happen (if not prevented) by diſheartning the good, and animating the ill affected; To order that all ſuch perſons, as have been in Armes againſt the Parliament, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants, and Neuters, may be removed from being Committees, or Commanders, and that their place may be ſupplyed with honeſt men, who have ventured their Lives, ſpent their Eſtates in, and for the Parliaments ſervice.</p>
            <closer>And they ſhall ever pray, &amp;c.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:159548:3"/>
            <head>The Coppy of a letter, ſent by Mr. <hi>John Muſgrave, Gent.</hi> to <hi>Alexander Rigby, Eſquire,</hi> a member of the Houſe of Commons.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>LIttle did <hi>I</hi> expect to have beene ſo troubleſome to my friends, upon ſuch an occaſion as this, ſitting a free Parliament: we were in hope when the High Commiſſion, Councell Board, and Starre-chamber were taken away according to the Law, that we had been free men and no more ſubject to any Arbitrary Power; But according to the Law, we ſhould have beene protected in our juſt Liberties, and have had juſtice done us without begging or intreaties; <hi>I</hi> have beene kept Priſoner here ſome 13. weekes, yet neither by ſolicitation of friends, or petitions, can <hi>I</hi> get audience, <hi>I</hi> deſire but the benefit of the Law, which <hi>I</hi> claim as my Right, either to bee juſtified or condemned, by the ſame; favour <hi>I</hi> deſire not, no other then the innocency of my cauſe deſerveth, Juſtice only <hi>I</hi> expect; as you have ever profeſſed your ſelfe to be the Common wealths ſervant, ſo <hi>I</hi> deſire you in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of my Country, to move the Houſe, that <hi>I</hi> may have my Liberty, being their Agent, and their Cauſe put in a way of Tryall. This is all <hi>I</hi> deſire from you, which <hi>I</hi> hope you will not deny me, and <hi>I</hi> ſhall bee</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From the</hi> Fleet <hi>Priſon</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of the firſt moneth 1646.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours to do you ſervice.</hi> John Muſgrave.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:159548:4"/>
            <head>The coppie of a letter ſent by Mr. <hi>John Muſgrave,</hi> to Sir <hi>Arthur Haſilrigge,</hi> Knight, a Member of the Houſe of Commons.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Am given to underſtand, that my petitions and letters of late publiſhed by ſome of my wel-wiſhers under the title of A word to the Wiſe, were delivered unto you by Mr. <hi>Peters;</hi> there is nothing in any of theſe petitions and letters which are mine, but I am ready to owne and avow; and if <hi>I</hi> may have but common juſtice and an equall hearing, I doubt not but to make good the ſame, to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to law and truth I am informed that you alone have taken upon you to be my judge, and have already condemned me, and caſt many vile aſperſions upon me giving forth how I comply with the <hi>Scotts,</hi> to drive on ſome wicked deſigne of theirs, tending to the prejudice of the State, and undoing of my Countrey, which if it were true, then are you blame-worthy to paſſe by the ſame, and not to bring me forth to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digne puniſhment: for already you have given out ſentence and adjudged me guilty though younever heard me ſpeak, and <hi>(I</hi> ſuppoſe) never knew me by face: but howſoever, though I were guilty of that wherein you condemneme, yet it doth not beſeeme you, nor any in the place of iudicature (as you are) to condemne any man unheard, and who is abſent, nor to have reſpect of perſons in iudgement; And none but unrighteous iudges, will doe ſo, for it is good and agreeable to law what <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith. <hi>Qui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                     <desc>•••…</desc>
                  </gap>d ſtatuerit altera parte inauditu aequ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m licet ſtatuerit hand aequus eſt,</hi> He that determineth and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth any thing, the one partie being unheard, although he determine and order that which is right, yet is he uniuſt. And this your doing is the more grievous, in that you inſult over a poore priſoner, whom you now have in bonds, and ſo not in place to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for himſelfe.</p>
            <p>I complaine of Traytors whom you ſuffer to walke at libertie, I have given in charges againſt them unto you, yet cannot get them brought to anſwer, whiles I am caſt into priſon before any charge be brought againſt me, put to anſwer interrogatories, and no accuſers comming againſt me. Traitors whom I accuſe are continued in their authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, yet almoſt foure months have I laine in priſon, and know not for what, but hether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, neither by friends nor petitions could I ever obtaine that favour and right (which of dutie you owe me, and all the free borne of this Kingdome) to have audience and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie as a free man to anſwer for my ſelfe: for as you can exact no obedience of us further then by the law, ſo may we boldly claime iuſtice according to the law, which to deny us, is iniuſtice in you by the law.</p>
            <p>I am blamed becauſe I decline the Committee, how ſhould I expect any good from them, when they dare not or will not ſuffer our cauſe to be publiquely heard and deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but doe ſhut their doores againſt both our friends and alſo againſt ſtrangers, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to law, yet ſuffer they our adverſaries whom we accuſe, to ſit with their hats on, as iudges in the cauſe, both permitting them and they taking upon them to examine us. O England (ſaith one) well in the like caſe, what's become of thy liberties? For if Sir <hi>Edward Cooke</hi> ſpake truth or knew the law, that iudge who ordereth and ruleth a cauſe in his chamber, though his order or rule be iuſt, yet offendeth he the law<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he rendereth is, for that all cauſes ought to be heard, ordered and determined openly in the Kings Courts, whether all perſons may reſort, and not in chambers or other pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate places. See <hi>Cooke</hi> 2. part inſtit. fol. 103.</p>
            <p>And how can I aſſent unto the Committ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es demands, to bring witneſſes to be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned before ſuch a Committee as cannot, or is not authorized to adminiſter an oath, and ſo conſequently cannot determine or give any iudgement for or againſt the partie accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, for that all matters of fact and cauſes criminall are to be tryed and determined by
<pb facs="tcp:159548:4"/>
the verdict of 12. men, upon the ſolemne oaths and depoſitions of witneſſes. See <hi>Cook</hi> 3. part inſtit. fol. 163. And how can I without incurring the haynous ſin of periury, ſubmit unto the arbitrary proceedings and determinations of any Committee, being bound by ſolemne oath and proteſtation, to maintaine the lawes and iuſt liberties of the people, and that the proceedings, orders, and reſults of the Committees be arbitrary, and not regulated by the law. I need no further proofe, then that exorbitant and unlimitted power they take upon them, and daily exerciſe in ſeizing on free mens goods, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoning their bodies contrary to law, For which if they ſhould as they ought pay 500. l, a peece &amp; treble damages to every party grieved according to the ſtatute of 17. <hi>Car.</hi> made for the aboliſhing of the Starchamber, I beleeve they would not adventure ſo boldly to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe: <hi>ſed impunitas continuum affectum tribuit delinquendi,</hi> but neglect of puniſhment, giveth boldneſſe to tranſgreſſe. Nay, I am verily perſwaded, the whole eſtates of many of them, would not give halfe ſatisfaction for the wrongs done by them. That this law were put in execution againſt ſuch lawleſſe men is my earneſt deſire, and daily expect the ſame.</p>
            <p>But it ſeemes you are much diſpleaſed that we ſhould impeach a member of your houſe, why? have you any priviledge to tranſgreſſe? To be a Parliament man, is it a good plea in Bar? I ever thought this warre had been undertaken for the preſervation and defence of our lawes and iuſt liberties, and not for ſheltering nor protecting any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents or offenders? Can it ſtand with your honours, your oaths, your truſts, your proteſtations and declarations to refuſe the delivering up your delinquent members to the law, to ſlight our iuſt complaints, and to caſt us into priſon for complaining? Can it ſtand with iuſtice and law, for the truſtees of the law, to plead priviledge and exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the law? Were not this to iuſtifie tranſgreſſion by a law? Doth not the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the law generally without any limitation or exemption concerne all equaly and alike? Is not the practice and execution, the very life and ſoule of the law? And what ſaith learned <hi>Cooke?</hi> neither can a iudge puniſh extortion, who is corrupted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, neither any Magiſtrate puniſh any ſin as he ought, that is knowne to be an offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der therein himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Therefore (ſaith he in the ſame place) it is an incident inſeparable to good govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the Magiſtrates to whom the execution of the lawes is committed, to be principall obſervers of the ſame themſelves, <hi>Cooke</hi> lib. 4. pref. Have not you complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned often times expreſſing great griefe, for that the King would not deliver up his evill counſellors and bad ſervants to be tryed by the law? and can we expect leſſe from you, then you exact of others, even of the King himſelf? For my part, I cannot deem them leſſe then guilty to themſelves, who under pretence or ſhadow of any priviledge, goe about to avoide the tryall of the law, and ſo thinke to eſcape with <hi>Ioab</hi> by flying to the hornes of the Altar.</p>
            <p>If Mr <hi>Liſle</hi> (Chair man of the Committee, where unto our cauſe was referred, and under whoſe bare report without any further ground I ſuffer) had been as truely zealous for the law, as he would be accounted knowing in the law, and had been as faithfull in diſcharging his truſt, by doing good offices for the publique, as he hath been ready to procure by his puolique place in the houſe, contrary to the ſelfe denying ordinance, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and profitable offices to himſelfe, he would not have laid our papers and informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions aſide, to the great damage and danger of our Countrey, nor ſo falne upon us as guiltie perſons by propounding interrogatories to inſnare us, even before he had any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection from the Houſe ſo to do he would have not miſreported to the houſe, that <hi>I</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuouſly refuſed to anſwer, whereas only according to law, <hi>I</hi> re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>d time to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. He would not have (ſo contrary to law) denyed to have given me and my fellow Commiſſioner the interrogatories, nor hindered us to write them from his mouth.
<pb facs="tcp:159548:5"/>
Neither would he have refuſed to give us a reaſonable time, to have adviſed according to the law, for anſwer; ſo (that either he muſt to his ſhame being a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor of the lawes, plead ignorance of the law, (which is his beſt plea) or elſe theſe his practiſes doe diſcover him to be faithleſſe, corrupt and uniuſt, and one of thoſe to whom it is ſaid, woe to you lawyers.</p>
            <p>For it appeareth by Sir <hi>Edward Cooke</hi> 2. part inſtit. fol. 51. that <hi>I</hi> ought by law to have had time allowed me wherein to adviſe for anſwer, his words be theſe. If anyone be ſuſpected for any crime, be it treaſon, fellony, &amp;c. and the partie be to be examined up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on interrogatories, he may take a reaſonable time to anſwer the ſame with deliberation, and the examinate (if he will) may put his anſwer in writing, and keep a coppie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and ſo it was reſolved in Parliament in the caſe of Juſtice <hi>Richel.</hi> See the record at large. 1. <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. memb. 2. num. 2. O yee Senatours, learne wiſedome, and take heed how yee either indanger your ſelves or us the free borne people of England whom yee repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And though we truſt you with our great affaires, yet doe not you truſt too much thoſe Lawyers, by whom our liberties have been ſo often betrayed, that except ſome few, like noble St. <hi>Johns;</hi> they are all ſo mercinarie, that even thoſe who ſit in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are nor aſhamed to take fees, and moneyes, for pleading cauſes depending in that high and honourable court, as they doe alſo in all other courts of iuſtice in Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter hall, and how ſhort they come in diſcharge of the truſt committed unto them, let the preceeding practice of Mr. <hi>Lile</hi> towards me (now a priſoner and agent for the well affected of <hi>Comberland</hi> and <hi>Weſtmoreland</hi> to the Parliament) beare witneſſe.</p>
            <p>As touching our charge againſt Mr <hi>Barwis</hi> and the reſt, it is evident that they are to be tryed at the Common law, and thus I prove it, the charge is for treaſons committed by them againſt the ſtate. And in Magna Charta cap. 29. it is declared, that no free man ſhall be taken or imdriſoned, or diſſeiſed of his free-hold, or liberties, or free cuſtomes, or be out-lawed, neither will we paſſe upon him, neither will wee ſit in judgement upon him, but by the lawfull judgement of his Peeres, or by the law of the land, and to no man will we ſell, deny, or delay juſtice or right. And hereby that crooked coard (as ſaith <hi>Cooke</hi> in 2. part inſtit. fol. 56) of that which is called diſcretion appeareth to be unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, unles you take it as it ought to be taken <hi>diſcretio est diſcernere, per legem, quid ſit juſt um,</hi> diſcretion is to diſcerne by the law what is juſt. And (there he ſaith) it is called right, becauſe it is the beſt birth-right that the ſubiect hath, for thereby his goods, lands, wife, children, his body, life, honour and eſtimation are protected from injury and wrong, adding the words of <hi>Citero, Maior hereditas venit, unicuique noſtrum aiure et legibus, quam a parentibus,</hi> A far greater and better inheritance diſcends unto each one of us from iuſtice and the lawes, then from our parents. And in his proeme to his 3. part inſtit. He urgeth that ancient maxime of the law, <hi>Miſera ſervitus eſt, ubi i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> eſt vagum vel incognitum,</hi> It is a miſerable bondage, where the law is uncertaine and unknown.</p>
            <p>And in the 24. page of the ſame booke: he telleth us how treaſons are to be tryed ſaying, there is another excellent branch of a ſtatute made 1. <hi>et. 2. Philip. et. Mar.</hi> cap, 10. in theſe words, Be it further inacted by authoritie aforeſaid, that all tryalls to bee had, awarded, or made for any treaſon, ſhall be had and uſed only according to the due order and courſe of the common law, which Statute is yet ſtill in as great force as firſt when it was made, the ſame never being repealed, for according thereunto yee tryed the Earle of <hi>Strafford</hi> ſince this preſent Parliament began, who had as good right to have challenged his priveledge and exemption from the common law (if any ſuch appeale had been) as ever Mr. <hi>Barwis</hi> had or any other who ſo ever, and which doubtleſſe hee would have done, and you have granted. At whoſe tryall <hi>I</hi> was, and you made uſe of mee as a witneſſe againſt him, where <hi>I</hi> was examined viva voce upon oath, the Earſe himſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:159548:5"/>
having firſt anſwered his charge according to law: Where by you may perceive it is plain and evident, that this our cauſe and charge is not proper nor pertinent to be tryed by any Committee, who are not authorized to adminiſter an oath, where by to put an end to any controverſie, but altogether ſuch courts of iuſtice as are inabled to begin and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed and end in a iudiciall way, <hi>per legem et conſuetudmem Angltae,</hi> by the law and cuſtome of this realme. For no priveledge of Parliament can hold or be pleaded in caſes of treaſon, fellony, and the peace, <hi>Cooke</hi> 4. part inſtit. fol. 15, Herein there only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines then to be done on your parts, ro give up your delinquent members to the law, and we on our parts according to the ſame law, to make good our charge by a due and legall proſecution.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, that <hi>I</hi> have combined with the <hi>Scotts,</hi> and drive on their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked deſigoe, give me leave to tell you that <hi>I</hi> being driven into exile through the crueltie of thoſe unnaturall vipers and traytors of my owne countrey, who joyned with the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh conſpirators in this great rebellion, to ruine our ſtate and countrey, they thirſting after my blood; and thinking to devoure me, profered large ſums of money, to ſuch as could apprehend me, <hi>I</hi> was forced to fly for my life, not being able of my ſelfe, to reſiſt their fury. After theſe your Committee men with us, had ſhamefully deſarted me and this iuſt cauſe of the kingdome, and adhered to the enemie, <hi>I</hi> having then no other way open nor apparent meanes to eſcape with much difficulty and more danger, got (by Gods good providence) into <hi>Scotland,</hi> where <hi>I</hi> indured no ſmall tryalls and troubles through the malignancie of ſome of their Miniſters and ſuch as they ſturred up againſt me, taking occaſion upon my non-conformitie and refuſall to come to their aſſemblies and high places, unto which <hi>I</hi> could not ſubmit nor ioyne my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>But after much and long ſtrugling and contention with theſe Miniſters, in the meane time labouring to walke inoffenſively towards them and all others in all other things, by the private meanes, and ſecret intelligence of ſome of my faithfull friends in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, then in bonds for the Parliaments cauſe, <hi>I</hi> diſcovered ſeverall deſignes of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, and our gentry againſt that ſtate, for which <hi>I</hi> found ſuch favour from the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates there, that the governour of <hi>Drumfreis</hi> did take me under protection, and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me from the perſecution and violence of my adverſaries there, wherein he ſhewed himſelfe to be truly noble, and for which <hi>I</hi> cannot but acknowledge my ſelfe to be much bound unto him; yea and the more in that neither I nor any of my iudgement, have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the like duty of love at home, notwithſtanding the diſcoveries and all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſervices we have done, neither ſparing our blood, nor regarding our eſtates for the good of the publique.</p>
            <p>After the reducement of <hi>Cumberland</hi> by the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> horſe, upon my returne thither from <hi>Scotland</hi> (being in exile a yeare and a halfe there) ſome of Mr. <hi>Barwis</hi> favourers &amp; boſome friends (who knew me in <hi>Scotland</hi> and of the good ſervice <hi>I</hi> had done there) threatned to root out me and all of my iudgement in our countrey. Neither did Mr. <hi>Barwis</hi> himſelfe regard any honeſt man there, though here (as <hi>I</hi> am informed) he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to be an Independant, but held up and countenanced the booke of Common pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer, (that Engliſh maſſe,) notwithſtanding all his ſolemne oaths, covenants, and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations againſt it: and likewiſe did put in the greateſt places of truſt and command with us, traitors and malignants, and men diſaffected to the publique good of this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. All his owne kinred being ſuch, whom he thus endeavoured to promote and make great, wherof we complaining to him, were altogether ſlighted, and thoſe our enemies his friends, kindred and allyes borne out and continued by him in their authorities, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would he give us any kind of aſſiſtance for releiving ſome honeſt and godly men, who had been kept long, and were then ſtill priſoners in <hi>Carlile</hi> by the enemie for the Parliaments cauſe, and who afterwards by the helpe of the <hi>Scotts</hi> were relieved out of
<pb facs="tcp:159548:6"/>
priſon, whiles <hi>I</hi> was at <hi>London</hi> ſoliciting this our countries cauſe, ſome of them being of the ſeparation.</p>
            <p>Sir, I was the laſt Winter here in Town above 3. moneths, expecting that Mr. <hi>Blaxton</hi> one of the Burgeſſes for <hi>New-Caſtle,</hi> according to his undertaking, would have preferred my petitions and charges againſt Mr. <hi>Barwis</hi> and other enemies of our Countrey; which he did not; And upon my return to the Country, Mr. <hi>Blaxton</hi> promiſed, that in my ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence with the firſt opportunitie, he would preſent to the honourable houſe of Commons thoſe my petitions and countrey grievances, wiſhing me to encourage my Countrey men, to preſſe on our juſt complaints, and he would bee aſſiſting unto us, and likewiſe I ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited ſome of the Committee of both Kingdomes at Goldſmiths Hall, namely Mr. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yor</hi> and Mr. <hi>Allen,</hi> (now a Parliament man) who alſo promiſing much, but after 5. weeks attendance upon them, by their owne direction, they performed nothing, Where (by the way) I deſire you to take notice, that in all this time whiles I thus attended with great wearineſſe, much diſcouragement and no ſmall expences, I did not ſo much as interchange one word with any of the Scots Comiſſioners, neither was I known to any of them by face.</p>
            <p>But upon our returne againe from our Country, to preſent our grievances, with ſeverall Letters to Mr. <hi>Blaxton</hi> to that purpoſe, we found him changed, and become our adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which did not a little trouble us, in reſpect of the intereſt which we conceived we had in him. But afterwards, by means of one Mrs. <hi>Glancroſſe,</hi> (a gentlewoman well known to many of our friends of the Separation) after we had beene in Town ſundry weeks, were made known to the L. of <hi>Wariſton,</hi> one of the Scottiſh Commiſſioners, who upon peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of our ſeverall charges againſt thoſe our adverſaries, did promiſe, that he would uſe his endeavour to get the ſame preſented to the Houſe, which not many daies after hee did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, And thus as my ends and intentions herein were reall and honeſt, ſo I hope the means which I uſed to attaine thereunto, were no wiſe unlawfull nor indirect: But as I cannot flatter, neither give vaine titles to any, ſo <hi>I</hi> hold it ignoble and baſe to bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull, either by neglecting ſuch perſons or not acknowledging ſuch favours, and the rather that they proceeded from ſtrangers, when as my owne Country men, who both of duty and by oath were bound unto us, ſo unworthily, ſo long delayed, and at laſt refuſed, ſo that they both neglected us, and ſleighted our cauſe and Country:</p>
            <p>Let others ſay and do what they pleaſe, as I am not aſhamed to owne and acknowledge favours received from my noble friends, ſo for my part, (as Lieut. Col. <hi>Lilburne</hi> ſpeaking of the juſtice done to him by the Houſe of Peers, ſaith in his book intituled, Innocency and truth juſtified, Pag. 75.) I am reſolved to ſpeake well of thoſe that have done mee ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and not to doubt they will deny it me, till ſuch time as by experience I find they doe it. Sir if I had found the like timely juſtice from you, I would neither have had ſo much cauſe thus to complain, nor to have been ſo much beholden to ſtrangers: whom the Parliament have ſtill accounted friends: And if you for your own part, had beene as tender of your friends, to whom you profeſſe kindneſſe, and to your Country to whom you owe duty; as I have alwaies been, and ſtill am ready to approve my ſelfe at all times in all faithfullneſſe to my Country, and forwardneſſe to promote their juſt cauſe wherewith I am intruſted, and which hath purchaſt no ſmall envy of the great enemies of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, I do verily beleeve that ſome of your ſuffering friends in the like condition with me who have relyed ſo much upon, you, had not been ſo fruſtrated in their expectation, and driven to ſo great ſtraites as to ſeek that comfort which you profeſſed, and might with eaſe have afforded.</p>
            <p>And you would have been more ready to have vouchſafed your aſſiſtance to have brought Traytors and enemies to the common wealth to condigne puniſhment, according to your ſeverall oaths, proteſtations, and ſubſcriptions, and would have beene aſhamed that traitors ſhould have walked at large in <hi>London</hi> ſtreets, whilſt your cordiall friends their proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors
<pb facs="tcp:159548:6"/>
are caſt and kept by you in priſon, for no other cauſe, wherewith they can be iuſtly charged, but for that they ſtand for the lawes and iuſt liberties of this kingdome, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would you have been ſo cenſorious to condemne that man whom the wel-affected of his countrey have thus intruſted, and on whom they doe ſtill relye, and againſt whom you know nothing, but bare and groundleſſe reports, and under hand calumniations, which no iudicious, generous, nor truly honeſt man will beleive: yet if you be not reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved againſt knowledge to act, or if there be any hope to recover and bring you to a right underſtanding of our countreys cauſe, my earneſt deſire is to undeceive you, if poſſioly <hi>I</hi> can, and have the more inlarged my ſelfe, the better to informe you of the true ſtate thereof.</p>
            <p>And <hi>I</hi> doe aſſure you if <hi>I</hi> may have iuſtice done me by mine owne countrey men, <hi>I</hi> will never ſeeke unto ſtrangers: for it was no ſmall griefe unto me, that from none of mine owne nation, <hi>I</hi> could obtain ſo much favour, neither by intreaties, nor recommendations, as to preſent the iuſt complaints of two counties, which ſo much concerned the weal and ſafety of two kingdomes, but was driven to that extremitie, even to have returned home to our owne Countrey, (which is nigh 300. miles diſtant) without any hope of ſo much as getting a petition preſented to the Houſe of Commons, if by meanes (under God) of the Lord of <hi>Warriſton</hi> (to whom before <hi>I</hi> was never known by face) thoſe our grievances by petition and articles had not been put up to the Houſe.</p>
            <p>By all which paſſages you may perceive how wickedly <hi>I</hi> am dealt with, and traduced by the friends and favorites of our and our Countries enemies, ſo that <hi>I</hi> may truly ſay, that the ſlanders of my adverſaries, is more quicke then any martiall law, for by them <hi>I</hi> have been arraigned, condemned, and executed all in one inſtant, if in a mans good name doth conſiſt his life and honour, your ſelfe being iudge. However give me leave to tell you, if <hi>I</hi> may obtaine that favour from you, as to mediate for me into the houſe of Commons, and in my behalfe, to preſent unto them this petition here incloſed, to the intent my countries iuſt cauſe may be put into a way of tryall: And whatſoever my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries ſay, I will engage my ſelfe in the behalfe of my countrey to proſecute the ſame to a full period, and make good our charge againſt them, or otherwiſe (as <hi>I</hi> have former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offered by my letter to Mr <hi>Speaker)</hi> to undergoe ſuch penaltie and puniſhment as by the rigour of the law may be inflicted upon me.</p>
            <p>And in the meane time, J would have my adverſaries to underſtand, that I am nothing eaſt downe, though layed and kept by their meanes in priſon, but ſtill relying upon God and the ſtrength and truth of my cauſe, and the iuſtice of the Parliament; and reſolved, though freedom were made capitall, and truth accompted never ſo offenſive, not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſh nor deſert the iuſt cauſe of my countrey, but in all loyall obedience to authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, my endeavours ſhall be to perſorme that duty which <hi>I</hi> owe to my countrey, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge that truſt they have committed unto me. Yea, and to my utmoſt power (by all lawfull wayes and meanes) according to my oath and proteſtation, to ſet my ſelfe againſt the ſactions and attemps of the adverſarie, in the defence of the lawes and our iuſt liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, wherein I ſhall not ſpare to ſpend my ſelfe, and put to hazard whatſoever is neareſt and deareſt unto me, and ſo I wiſh you may account it to be your honour, whom we have honoured to chuſe as our truſties, to ſit at the helme of this our toſſed ſhip, in ſuch an oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an of tempeſtuous waves, even to execute righteous iudgement, as yee wiſh to come to a fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re haven, and as ye labour to deſtroy your cruell enemies, ſo to protect your truſtie friends, who have in all aſſaults and extremiteis never relinquiſhed you, nor the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon cauſe of this diſtreſſed kingdome: thus hoping yee will all unanimouſly uſe your beſt endeavours to deliver us, your ſelves and the poſteritie from all the bondage and oppreſſion which is now exerciſed over this bleeding nation, and reſtore us to our anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent liberties at leaſt, which our anceſtors by their blood ſo dearly purchaſt, that hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth we may injoy peace and truth, with the adminiſtration of iuſtice, which is the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſute and ſervent deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your faithfull friend in all due reſpects <hi>John M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4+ letters">
                        <desc>••••…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </signed>

               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
               <signed>John Muſgrave.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <pb facs="tcp:159548:7"/>
               <p>Sir, I forgot one thing, which I deſire to be cleared, which is, the Scottiſh wicked deſigne (as you are pleaſed to tearm it) I pray you, if you ſuſpect any ſuch thing, and yet know it not fully, why do not you either ask themſelves? for they are old enough<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or elſe deal with them; for ye call them brethren, yea, and not only have ſolemnly ſworne and covenanted with them your ſelves, but urge all of this Nation under your power ſo to do, and therefore lay the blame on thoſe who ought to bear it, but never on me, nor any of my judgement: becauſe both ye, and the Scots know well enough, that we are not minded to ſubmit to their Presbyterian government, what ever it coſt us ſo if that be the wicked deſigne you mean (for neither do I know, nor I ſuppoſe themſelves intends any other) you are very much miſtaken in me, for I, and all of my mind, are rather adjudged to be ſufferers, then any wiſe accounted to be actors therein, as you very well know by all our writings and practices, in which you have already condemned us, though you would never give us a fair hearing, nor convince us according to the word of God, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in that little book called, <hi>The lawfulnes of the Scots comming into England,</hi> pag. 6. reaſ. 6. Where it is ſaid, at the accompliſhing of this bleſſed Reformation there inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded (as both their and your miniſters, the true drivers on of ſuch wicked deſignes if any be, are pleaſed to call it) even that there ſhall not be a papiſt, ſeparatiſt, nor ſecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry any more mentioned, if this be not the meaning of that place (being paraleld both with your and their practiſes ſince, then I deſire, that there might be a toleration in the one according to the word of truth, and a reſolution in the other, according to equitie and reaſon: however, go on, and do what you pleaſe, I, and others of my judgement will reſt upon God, who will make all things work together for the beſt unto thoſe that fear him.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <head>To the right Honourable, the Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes, of the Commons Houſe in Parliament aſſembed:</head>
            <opener>The humble Petition of <hi>John Muſgrave, Gentleman,</hi> priſoner in the Fleet. <hi>Sheweth,</hi>
            </opener>
            <p>THat I, with one <hi>Iohn Oſmotherly,</hi> were intruſted by the Parliaments friends, the well affected party in <hi>Cumberland,</hi> and <hi>Weſtmerland,</hi> to preſent their grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances to this honourable Houſe, by reaſon of the plots and cruel oppreſſions of ſome who have formerly betrayed their truſt, ſtirred up the King to this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall wat, borne armes with the King to deſtroy this honourable Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſuch as ſtood for them, put in execution the Commiſſion of Array, and other il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legall taxes, and forced the free-born people of this kingdome to an arbitrary govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; all which perſons have been declared by this preſent Parliament, to betraytors by the fundamentall laws of this Kingdom: the Parliaments owne words in the book of Declarations <hi>(fol.</hi> 260.) are theſe. <hi>Reſolved upon the queſtion, That who ſoever ſhall ſerve or aſſist him (meaning the King) in the wars againſt his people, are traytors by the fundamentall Laws of this Kingdom, and have been ſo adjudged by two Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ought to ſuffer as traytors.</hi> 11. <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. <hi>and</hi> 1. <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. But ſo it is, that theſe perſons (upon the comming in of the Scottiſh Army, the Countrey being reduced to the obedience of the Parliament) are now ſet up in the chief places of truſt and command, by the Commiſſioners of that high and honourable Court ſent into the countrey, by which means they are enabled to cover and protect all ſuch as have formerly joyned with them in theſe bloody wars, and to oppreſſe the Parliaments friends, the well affected partie as
<pb facs="tcp:159548:7"/>
much now, or more, then when they were open proſeſſed enemies, bearing armes for the King.</p>
            <p>And I, with others, having preſented our Countries grievances to Mr. <hi>Richard Barwls</hi> a Member of this honourable Houſe, and Burges for the City of <hi>Garlile,</hi> and to the reſt of the Commiſſioners in the Countrey, who ſat up theſe men in military affairs, and Committees for Sequeſtrations, and other taxes; but they affording no relief to us and to the well affected of both theſe Counties, deſired and procured me and my fellow com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner, to preſent their grievances to this honourable Parliament, hoping for reliefe, according to their proteſtations, declarations, ſubſcriptions, oaths, and covenants, to eaſe the opreſſed, and puniſh the oppreſſors, where I have attended ſince <hi>April</hi> laſt, beſides three moneths the laſt winter, uſing all lawfull meanes that I and the other Commiſſioner could, both to members of this honourable Houſe, and certain of the Committee of both Kingdoms, and diverſe common Councell men of <hi>London</hi> to get this our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries cauſe put into a legall way of tryall, but ſtill being fruſtrated of preſenting the ſame to this honourable Houſe in the moneth of <hi>Iune</hi> laſt, by a providence, we came to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Scottiſh Commiſſioners, who (perceiving that the ſetling of thoſe two Counties, would be for the good of both Kingdoms) undertook to aſſist us, and to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our grievances to this honourable Houſe, who procured the ſame with their own pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, to be referred to a Committee, whereof Mr. <hi>Liſle</hi> is chair-man, who laid aſide all our papers, and would have examined us upon interrogatories: but we declared that we were Commiſſioners for the Countrey, and had given in a charge againſt Mr <hi>Richard Barwis</hi> and others, by Counſell, and therefore deſired that the ſame might be put into a way of tryall: And if Mr. <hi>Rich. Barwis</hi> and others of whom we complained, ſhould deny any thing which we have given in charge againſt them, that we ſhould make it good by ſufficient witheſſes, or elſe ſuffer according to law.</p>
            <p>Then the Committe deſired power from this Honourable Houſe to examine us upon interrogatories, and if we ſhould refuſe, to commit us to priſon, and ſo obtaining power (which they had not before) preffed us to anſwer interrogatories, and when we deſired a copie thereof, or to write the ſame from their own mouth, and we would anſwer accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to law, by the advice of Councell, which they denyed us, but ſtill they requiring us to anſwer <hi>ex tempore,</hi> and we conceiving that we were not bound ſo to do by law, could not thereunto conſent. Then report being made to this honourable Houſe, that we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to anſwer, which we did not, but in caſe aforeſaid, this honourable Houſe ordered me to be committed to the priſon of the <hi>fleet,</hi> where I have lain theſe 4. months: and my fellow Commiſſioner being vexed by Mr. <hi>Iohn Fiſher,</hi> was committed alſo to priſon, for apretended debt: And after he was releaſed by vertue of an ordinance of Parliament for ſecuring Commiſſioners, and ſuch others as did attend upon this honourable Houſe, for preſenting of Countrey grievances, yet by the means and direction of Iuſtice <hi>Whitaker,</hi> chairman of the Committee of Examinations, the ſaid <hi>John Oſmotherly</hi> was committed again to priſon in <hi>Woodſtreet Counter,</hi> where he was put to great charges to free himſelf by a writt, of <hi>Habes Corpus</hi> from the Chancery, where the ſuit is depending: but by the potency and policy of ſome, he was ſo purſued (even after he was laſt releaſed) that he could not walk <hi>London</hi> ſtreets, for diverſity of Bayliffes, who were ready awaiting upon all occaſions, to arreſt him, where upon he was forced to return to his Countrey, and the ſaid Iuſtice <hi>Whitaker</hi> (before I was committed to the Fleet, whilſt we both were to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend on that Committee, where of Mr. <hi>Liſle</hi> is chair man) iſſued out his warrant to ſearch my chamber for ſuſpected papers againſt the State, and to attach my body, by vertue wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, my chamber was ſearched in the night time, and my ſelf apprehended, and brought before the Committee of Examinations, and kept under a meſſengers cuſtody eight daies before I could procure a diſcharge, and when I was brought before that Committee, they
<pb facs="tcp:159548:8"/>
had nothing to lay to my charge, but did propound interrogatories (as <hi>I</hi> conceive) to inſnare me, All which practiſes did and do tend to the obſtruction of our Countrey buſines, if not to the ruine of the Countrey it ſelf, had not ſome of the Scots forces pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented the incurſions of <hi>Digby</hi> and <hi>Longdale;</hi> and they that had the chiefeſt command in martiall affairs (againſt whom we complain) doing nothing conſiderable to preſerve the Countrey, though they had command and power to have done what was needfull, and many of them ſince my impriſonment have come to <hi>London</hi> to compound for their delinquency and treaſons, paying ſome part of that whereof they have wronged the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and not making any reparation to the poor oppreſſed people.</p>
            <p>Therefore my humble requeſt is, that I may be permitted according to law, to anſwer, and I doubt not but to clear my ſelf of that ſuppoſed contempt, for which I was committed, and that my Countrey buſines may be put into a ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy way of tryall; and that thoſe whom this honourable Houſe, according to the fundamentall lawes of the land have declared to betraytors, and ſuch as kept correſpondency with them, may be put upon due tryall at common I'm, and juſtice no longer ſold, denyed, nor delayed, and that their lands and eſtate, according to law ſeized upon, and reparations made out of the ſame to the parties wronged, and ſuch men as are and have been the Parliaments friends, the well affected of the Countrey may be put in places of truſt and command</p>
            <closer>And as I am in duty bound, ſo ſhall <hi>I</hi> praiſe God, and pray for you.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>The Poſt ſcript,</head>
            <p>CVrteous Reader, thou maiſt very much wonder at the delatory and ſlow proceedings of the Houſe of Commons, in doing juſtice and right; from whom the Commons of <hi>England</hi> may juſtly expect more then from any other Judicatory, being they are ime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly choſen by them; and to ſpeak properly, are no more but their ſtewards and ſervants for whoſe good and benefit all their actions ought to be extended, and ought in honeſtly and right to have but one and the ſame intereſt with them, but no diſtinct ſelf-intereſt from them: Yet by their proceedings daily, we ſee it is in vaine to expect juſtice from them, ſo long as they are ſo linkt and glude in factions each to other by their private in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, in their great places, which ties all ſuch amongſt them to maintain one another in all their unjuſt waies, and to oppreſſe and cruſh as much as they are able, all the proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuters of juſt and righteous things, and ſo to barre and ſtop juſtice that it ſhall have little or no progreſſe; divers of them, and their creatures, ſons, brothers, unkles, and kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and allies, in the ſub-committees, having already committed ſo much injuſtice, that they are undone in their blazed honour, and ill-gotten eſtates, if juſtice ſhould run in its native luſtre, and full current, and of neceſſity, they and then great places would quickly be deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>Otherfore that the freemen of <hi>England</hi> had but their eyes open, to ſee the miſchief of members of the Houſe of Commons (men of their own election &amp; chuſing to fit in the ſupream Court of <hi>England)</hi> to be intangled themſelves, or intermeddle with any other place whatſoever, then that whereunto their Countrey have choſen them! what a ſhame is it to ſee the mercinary long gown-men of the Houſe of Commons, to run up and down like ſo many hackney petty foggers, from bar to bar in <hi>Weſtminſter hall</hi> &amp;c. to plead be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore inferiour Judges, and to ingroſſe and monopolize, the greateſt part of the practiſe of the law, from other poore lawyers, although divers of theſe Parliament groſſes be recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Corporations beſides, who ought in Conſcience and reaſon to give way to their Corporations, to chuſe new Recorders in their places? for how is it poſſible that they
<pb facs="tcp:159548:8"/>
ſhould ſerve the Parliament as members thereof, and their Corporations as Recorders, at ſo many miles diſtance, and at one and the ſame time?</p>
            <p>And beſides, how can ſuch great practiſers chuſe but mercinarily be ingaged to helpe their clyents over a ſtile, in caſe that ever they have to do with any of their owne Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees, and what is this elſe, but to ſell juſtice for money? Beſides, what a ſnare is it to the new Judges (who are placed in the room of thoſe that have bought, ſold, and betraid the lives, liberties, and eſtates of all the free denizons of <hi>England?</hi> witnes their judgement in ſhip mony &amp;c. to ſee 3. or 4. eminent lawyers, members of the Houſe of Comons, come before them in an unjuſt cauſe; when they conſider, that if they ſhould diſpleaſe them, it partly lies in their power to turn them out of their places, being they are (as it were) wholy made Judges by the Houſe of Commons, and nominated by the Lawyers therein.</p>
            <p>We profeſſe ſeriouſly, that to pull the gownes over theſe mercinary mens eares, and forever to throw them out of the Houſe of Commons, as men unfit to ſit there, onto plead at any barre in England, is too little a puniſhment for them, the ſcum of mankind, and the ſame (we conceive) do they deſerve, that are members of that Houſe, and take upon them to ſit as judges in inferiour Courts, by means of which they rob the Freeman of <hi>England</hi> of the benefit of an appeal, in caſe of injuſtice, becauſe they have no where to appeal to, but the Parliament, where they ſit as judges in their own cauſe, which is a moſt wicked, intolerable, and unjuſt thing in any judge whatſoever: We hope ſhortly that if theſe men be not aſhamed of their evil herein, ſome honeſt and reſolute hearted Engliſhman, will be ſo bold as publiquely to poſt up their names as deſtroyers of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>And as great an evill is it to the Kingdom, for members of the Houſe of Commons, to take upon them to be fingerers and treaſurers of the publique money of the Kingdome, becauſe they are thereby in a condition to fill their own coffers, and do what wrong they pleaſe (or elſe how comes it to paſſe that ſo many of their children are ſo richly married of late, that were but mean before? and no man knowes how to call them to account, unleſſe they deal with them as the <hi>Romans</hi> ſometimes dealt with their Senators, or as the <hi>Switzers</hi> dealt with their tyrants: for the money is the Kingdomes, and not the members of the Houſe of Commons, and the Kingdom ought in Juſtice, reaſon, and right to have a publique, punctuall, and particular account of it; and therefore it ought not to be in the hands, or fingers of thoſe that are able to make ſo great a faction as are able to protect themſelves from Juſtice, and an exact account.</p>
            <p>O that that gallant man, L. G. <hi>Cromwel</hi> (to whom the Kingdom for their preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, under God, oweth ſo much, would a little more deny himſelf, and ceaſe to be a ſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king horſe, and a dangerous preſident, of moſt dangerous conſequence, to theſe wicked mercinary pluraliſts, non reſidentary, great placemen, for whom an Hoſpitall of any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence cannot fail, but they muſt be government, of it nor a putty place in the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap> bag office, but they muſt get into it: which men, of the Kingdome would rightly conſider it, have juſt cauſe to diſclaim as none of their patrons, but proclaime as their enemie and deſtroyers, being only pecuniary ſelf ſeekers.</p>
            <p>For ſo long as parliament men can per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> their hands the riches and treaſures of the Kingdom, and live like Kings and Emperours, and like lawleſſe men none ſuch being of Gods creation (for he never created a lawleſſe man) there will never be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> end of this Parliament, which by its everlaſting continuance, by the abuſes of lawleſſe and rotten hearted men <hi>(Machiavels</hi> ſons, whoſe principall it is, when he would deſtroy a State or Kingdom, and deliver them into the hands of their enemies; to put them upon ads of injuſtice, oppreſſion, and invading of the people right, which is the only way to effect their ruine and deſtruction) will become the muſt abſolute burthen, and greateſt oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that ever was upon the people: when as in times by paſt, it uſed to be their onely remedy from their oppreſſion, and oppreſſors.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:159548:9"/>
The thing that we wiſh L. G. <hi>Cromwel</hi> to conſider of, is this, that he was choſen a Burgeſſe for <hi>Cambridge,</hi> to ſit in Parliament, and not to be Lieut. Gen. of an Army, both which places he ought not in conſcience, nor cannot in equity, honeſty, and honour hold, but either muſt come and fit in Parliament, his proper place, or elſe he ought to adviſe and permit them to chuſe another Burgeſſe to ſit in his ſtead; which we conceive would be the greateſt and beſt peece of ſervice that ever he did the Parliament or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth in his life, (who both are in the high roade way of deſtruction, by theſe merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary pluraliſts, great place men) for to be a member of the Houſe of Commons is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to take up the whole and intire man, without deviding it, although he were five times wiſer then any man there appears to be: and if <hi>Cromwel</hi> would do his duty here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, their vail and preſident were taken of, and laid down, which would be for his excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding honour and glory, and the unſpeakable good of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Wherefore dear and beloved friend Mr. <hi>Muſgrave,</hi> ſeeing God hath given you the ſpirit of boldnes, wiſdom, underſtanding, zeal, and courage, lay it out more fully for the good of your Countrey, and ſpeedily preſent him with a home and plain Epiſtle for that end, and we alſo intreat you to make ſome obſervations to him, upon what you will find in the 19. 20. 21. pages of <hi>Englands birth-right,</hi> and preſſe them home to him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Curteous Reader,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the Lord Major of <hi>London</hi> his houſe, the 16th. of this ſecond moneth 1646. upon divers complaints made by the miniſters of <hi>London,</hi> againſt many pariſhes and particular Citizens, for not payment of tithes, and after ſeverall daies diſputations in free publick meetings at his hall, between the Plantiffes and defendants, by themſelves, and their learned Counſell, and many arguments diſcuſſed on both ſides, it was found at laſt, that howſoever th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe prieſts have exacted and received tithes a long time, yet altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly by the law both of God and man; for the one, Chriſt hath preſcribed voluntary maintenance for his paſtors to feed all his flocks, and for the other, that ſtatute of the 37. of <hi>H.</hi> 8. authoriſeth certain Commiſſioners, to make a decree for the paiment of tithes to the <hi>London</hi> Miniſters, and what they ſhall order and decree, ſhall be binding to the citizens of <hi>London,</hi> in caſe the decree be made by ſuch a day, and inrouled in the high Court of Chancery, but in caſe it be not inrouled there, it is no law, and ſo not binding, but Mr. <hi>Nerborow</hi> the citizens counſell, produced to the Lord Maior, a certificate under the Regiſters hand, that it neither is, nor never was inrouled: and therefore the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters may goe whiſſell for their tithes. Next, the tithes were given to maintaine thoſe prieſts who read ſervice, which none do now, becauſe the ſervice book is aboliſhed, and ſo no work, no wages. And thirdly, Though that Engliſh maſſe book were yet in force, theſe black-coats now are not the men for whom thoſe tithes were provided, but onely ſuch as were ordained by, and ſerv'd under the Biſhops: which ordination and ſervice theſe Prieſts now have not only renounced, but quite depoſed and rejected thoſe their maſters, And ſo if they be to ſeek new maſters, and new work, they muſt alſo ſeek new wages. Yet it is my advice, and <hi>I</hi> trow will be their beſt courſe, even to worke with their hands, as many better men do, and not to live idley by the ſweat of other mens browes.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 141. 5.</hi>
                  </bibl> Let the Righteous ſmite, it ſhall be a kindnes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and let him reproove me, it ſhall be an extellent oyl, which ſhall not break mine head: for yet my prayer alſo ſhall be in their calamities.</q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Proverbs 27. 6.</hi>
                  </bibl> Faithfull are the wounds of a friend, but the kiſſes of an enemy are deceitfull.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
